Only 3% of the
water on our planet is fresh
Yet these precious waters are rich with surprise
All life on land
is ultimately dependent upon fresh water
The mysterious
tepuis of Venezuela
Isolated mountain
plateaus rising high above the jungle
This was the inspiration for Arthur Conan Doyle's lost world
an imagined
prehistoric land
Here strange towers of sandstone have been sculptured over the millennia
by battering wind
and torrential rain
Moisture rising
as water vapour from the surface of the sea
is blown
inland by wind
On reaching mountains
the moist air
is forced upwards
And as it cools
it condenses into cloud
and finally rain
The source of
all fresh water
There is a tropical downpour here almost every day of the year
Freshwater's
journey starts here
high in
the mountains
Growing from
humble streams to mighty rivers
It will travel
hundreds of miles to the sea
Angel Falls
the highest
waterfall in the world
Its waters drop
unbroken for almost a thousand metres
Such is the
height of these falls
That long before
the water reaches the base
In the
Devil's Canyon
It's blown away
as a fine mist
In their
upper reaches
mountain streams
are full of energy
Streams join
to form rivers
building in power
creating rapids
The water
here is cold
low in nutrients
but high in oxygen
The few creatures
that live in the torrent
have to hang
on for dear life
Invertebrates
dominate these upper reaches
The hellgrammite
its body
flattened to reduce drag
has bushy gills
to extract oxygen from the current
Blackfly larvae
anchor themselves with a ring of hooks
But if these
become unstuck
they're still
held by a silken safety line
There are advantages to life in the fast stream
Bamboo shrimps
can just sit and sift out passing particles
With their
fanlike forearms
Usually
these mountain
streams only provide enough food
for small
animals to survive
But with the
spring melt
here in Japan
monsters stir
in their dens
Giant salamanders
the world's
largest amphibian
almost two
metres long
They're the only
large predator in these icy waters
They begin
their hunt at night
These salamanders
have an exceptionally slow metabolism
Living up
to 80 years
they grow
into giants
The fish they
hunt are scarce
And salamanders
have poor eyesight
But sensory nodes
on their head and body
Detect the slightest changes in water pressure
Free from
competition
these giants
can dine alone
Pickings are
usually thin for the salamanders
But every year
some of the world's high rivers
Are crowded by
millions of visitors
The salmon
have arrived
This is the world'
s largest freshwater fish migration
Across the
northern hemisphere
salmon returning
from the ocean to their spawning grounds
Battle their way
for hundreds of miles upstream
Up here
there are fewer
predators to eat their eggs and fry
A grizzly bear
From famine to feast
he's spoilt
for choice
This Canadian
bear is very special
He's learnt to
dive for his dinner
But catching
salmon in deep water
is not that easy
And the cubs
have lots to learn
The annual
arrival of spawning salmon
brings huge quantities of food into these high rivers
that normally
struggle to support much life
Although
relatively lifeless
the power of these upland rivers to shape the landscape
is greater than
any other stage in a river's life
Driven by gravity
they're the most
erosive forces on the planet
For the past
five million years
Arizona's
Colorado River
has eaten away at
the desert sandstone
to create a
gigantic canyon
It's over
a mile deep
and at its widest
it's 17
miles across
The Grand Canyon
This river has
cut the world's longest canyon system
A 1，000 miles
scar clearly visible from space
As rivers leave
the mountains behind
They
gradually warm
And begin to
support more life
Indian rivers are
home to the world's most social otters
Smooth coated
otters form family groups up to 17 strong
Group rubbing not
only refreshes their coats
but strengthens social bonds
When it
comes to fishing
there is real
strength in numbers
Fishing practice
begins when the cubs are four months old
Only the adults have the speed and agility needed to make a catch
Adults share their catches with their squabbling cubs
Most otters
are solitary
But these
rich warm waters
Can support
large family groups
And even
bigger predators
Mugger crocodiles
four metres long
could easily
take a single otter
But confident
in their gangs
the otters will
actively harass these great reptiles
Team play
wins the day
The Mara River
snaking across
the plains of East Africa
As the land
flattens out
rivers slow down
and lose their destructive power
Now they are
carrying heavy loads of sediment
That stains
their waters brown
Lines of wildebeest are on the march
Each year
nearly two million animals migrate across the Serengeti plains
In search of
fresh green pastures
For these
thirsty herds
the rivers are
not only a vital source of drinking water
But also
dangerous obstacles
This is one of the largest concentrations of Nile crocodiles in Africa
Giants that grow
over five metres long
From memory
the crocodiles
know the wildebeest are coming
and gather in
anticipation
The crocodile's
jaws snap tight like a steel trap
Once they
have a hold
they never let go
It took over an
hour to drown this fullgrown bull
To surprise
their prey
crocodiles must
strike with lightning speed
Here
only the narrowest line separates life from death
Most rivers
drain into the sea
But some end
their journey in vast lakes
Worldwide
lakes hold 20
times more fresh water
Than all
the rivers
The East African
Rift Valley holds three of the world's largest
Malawi，Tanganyika
and Victoria
Lake Malawi
the smallest
of the three
is still
bigger than Wales
Its tropical waters teem with more fish species than any other lake
There are 850
different cichlids alone
all of which
evolved from just one single ancestor
isolated here
thousands of years ago
These two metre
wide craters are fish made
Fastidiously
maintained by the males
these bowers are
courtship arenas
Cichlids are
caring parents
Brooding young in
the mouth is a very effective way of protecting them
This lake can be
a dangerous place
After dark
predatory dolphin
fish emerge from their daytime lairs among the rocks
Like packs
of sharks
they're on the
prowl for sleeping cichlids
In the darkness
these electric fishhunt by detecting distortions in the electric field
they create
around their bodies
Any cichlid
that ventures out
will be snapped up
The floor of Lake
Malawi drops 700 metres into an abyss
Here in
this dead zone
the larvae of lake fly midges hide out away from predators
In the
rainy season
they balloon up
to the surface
and undergo a
magical transformation
At dawn
the first adult
midges start to break out
Soon
millions upon
millions of newly hatched lake flies
are taking
to the wing
Early explorers
told tales of lakes that smoked
as if on fire
But these
spiralling columns
hundreds of
metres high
are making flies
Once the
flies have mated
they will all
drop to the water surface
release
their eggs
Molawi may look
like an inland sea
but it's dwarfed
by the world's largest lake
Baikal in
eastern Siberia
400 miles long
and over a mile deep
Baikal contains
one fifth of all the fresh water
found in our
planet's lakes and rivers
For five
months of the year
it's sealed by
an ice sheet over a metre thick
貝加爾湖係世界最古老嘅湖，而且
即使環境咁惡劣，生命喺呢度繁盛
80%嘅種類喺地球其他地方都見唔到
包括世界上唯一嘅淡水海象
With this seal
and its marinelike forests of sponges
Baikal seems more
like an ocean than a lake
There are
shrimplike crustaceans
giant amphipods
as large as mice
They are the key
scavengers in this lake
The water here
is just too cold
for the bacteria
that normally decompose the dead
Most rivers do
not end in lakes
But continue
their journey to the sea
The planet's
indisputable super river
Is the Amazon
It carries as much water as the next top ten biggest rivers combined
Rising in the
Peruvian Andes
Its main trunk
flows eastwards across Brazil
On its way
the system drains
a third of South America
Eventually
over 4000 miles
from its source
it empties into
the Atlantic Ocean
The Amazon transports a billion tons of sediment a year
Sediment clearly
visible at the mixing of the waters
Where one
massive tributary
the Rio Negro
flows into
the main river
Its waters are
wonderfully rich
To date
over 3000 species
of their fish have been described
More than in the
whole of the Atlantic Ocean
The Amazon is so
large and rich in fish
that it can
support freshwater dolphins
These
botoes are huge
two and a
half metres long
In these
murky waters
they rely on
sonar to navigate and hunt
They work together
to drive shoals
of fish into the shallows
Botoes are
highly social
And in the
breeding season
there is stiff
competition for mates
The males hold
court in a unique way
They pick up
rocks in their jaws
and flaunt them
to their attending females
Maybe each male is trying to show how strong and dexterous he is
and that
he therefore
is the best father a female could have for her young
Successful
displays lead to mating
Even for giant
rivers like the Amazon
the journey to the sea is not always smooth or uninterrupted
Iguassu Falls on
the border of Brazil and Argentina
is one of the
widest waterfalls in the world
one and a
half miles across
In flood
13 million litres
of water spill over every second
All the world's
great broad waterfalls
Victoria，Niagara
And here，Iguassu
Are only found in
the lower courses of their rivers
In their
final stages
Rivers broaden and flow wearily across their flat floodplains
Each wet season
here in Brazil
The Paraná River
overflows its banks
And floods an
area the size of England
The Pantanal
the world's
largest wetland
In these
slowflowing waters
aquatic
plants flourish
Like the Victoria
giant water lily
with leaves
two metres across
These underwater
forests are nursery grounds for fish
Over 300
species breed here
including
redbelly piranha
And other predators like the spectacle caiman
Ripening fig trees
overhanging
the water's edge
provide welcome
food for shoals of hungry fish
The commotion
attracts Dorado
known locally as
the river tiger
They patrol the
feeding shoals
looking for a
chance to strike
And waiting
in the wings
ready to pick off
any injured fish
are the piranhas
A feeding frenzy
quickly develops
Piranha can strip
a fish to the bone in minutes
Great numbers of
fish sustain vast flocks of waterbirds
The rosy at spoonbill is just one of the 650 bird species found in the Pantanal
They nest
alongside wood stalks
in colonies
thousands strong
Spectacle
caiman linger below
waiting for a
meal to fall out of the sky
When rivers
finally reach the sea
they slow down
release
their sediment
and build deltas
In Bangladesh
the Ganges and
Brahmaputra rivers join
to form the
world's biggest
Every year
almost 2000
million tons of sediment
eroded from
the Himalayas
is delivered
to the ocean
At the
delta's mouth
the largest
mangrove forest in the world
the Sundarbans
These extraordinary forests spring up throughout the tropics
In these
tidal zones
where rivers
meet the sea
Crabeating macaques are mangrove specialists
In Indonesia
these monkeys have adopted a unique amphibious lifestyle
They fish
out fallen food
The troop also
uses the waters
to cool off
during the heat of the day
But the channels
are also the playground
for restless
young macaques
Some of the young
have even taken to underwater swimming
They can stay
down for more than 30 seconds
And appear to do
this just for fun
Yet these
swimming skills
acquired
during play
will certainly be
useful later in life
in these flooded
mangrove forests
In cooler climes
mud laid
down in estuaries
is colonised by
saltmarsh grasses
and form one of
the most productive habitats on the planet
400，000
greater snow geese
flock to the estuaries along the Atlantic coast of the United States
To rest and refuel on their long migratory journeys
This is the end
of the rivers journey
Collectively
they've worn down
mountains and carried them to the sea
And all
along the way
their fresh water
has brought life and abundance
To planet Earth